Guide to the Frederick Alonzo North Papers MC.9
New York University Archives
Frederick Alonzo North Papers
1890-1906
New York University Archives
North, Frederick Alonzo, d. 1906
MC.9
1.5 Linear Feet
The Frederick Alonzo North Papers contain student notebooks, student compositions, lectures, reports, records, newspaper clippings, photographs, and books generated by Frederick Alonzo North, a public school teacher and administrator, traveler and lecturer, and student at NYU between 1894 and 1906.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is organized to correspond with North's occupations as student, lecturer, and principal and superintendent of the Ocean County Schools. Within each group, the material is arranged chronologically.
I. Student Notebooks II. Student Compositions III. Debate Notes IV. Lectures V. Notebooks VI. Ocean County Schools
Scope and Contents
The collection contains material generated by North as a student at New York University, Glen Falls National Summer School, and Clark University; as principal of Toms River High School, Toms River, New Jersey; as superintendent of the Ocean County Schools, Toms River, New Jersey; and from his career as a travel lecturer. Included are student notebooks, student compositions, lectures, reports, records, newspaper clippings, photographs, and books.
Biography of Frederick Alonzo North
Frederick Alonzo North was a public school teacher and administrator, traveler and lecturer, and student at NYU from 1894-1906. He taught school for twelve years in a variety of institutions, from country schools to the university level. He then served as principal of Plantsville School, Plantsville, Connecticut until 1892. From 1893-1896 he was the principal of Toms River High School in Toms River, New Jersey. North assumed the position of Superintendent of the Schools of Ocean County, New Jersey, in 1897 and served as such until 1902. He then began to travel quite extensively and to lecture on his travels under the authority of the Board of Education of Greater New York. He died while on an expedition to Peru in 1906 and is buried there.
North remained a student most of his life. He completed a regular college course and in the summers of 1891 and 1892 attended the National Summer School of Methods and Languages at Glen Falls, New York. In 1894 North enrolled in the School of Pedagogy of New York University and began working towards his Master of Pedagogy degree, which he earned in 1902. He continued at NYU to earn a Bachelor of Science in Pedagogy degree in 1904. In addition, he had secured by examination a first grade State Certificate, completed a law course, completed the Chautauqua Literary and Scientific Course, and attended the Clark University Summer School.
Sources: "Representative Ocean County Educators," The Courier. Biographical sketch of F.A. North as principal of Toms River High School, Toms River, N.J., 1896.
Voorhis, Harold O., Letter with biographical sketch accompanying transfer of collection to Archives, January 4, 1961.
Provenance
His papers were presented to the University in December 1960 by a grand-niece of Mr. North, Mrs. Ralph L. Gilman of Storrs, Connecticut. The collection came to the Archives through Harold O. Voorhis, then Vice President and Secretary of the University, who wrote a short biographical sketch of North to accompany the transfer.
Ocean County (N.J.); West Glen Falls (N.Y.); Clark University (Worcester, Mass.); New York University. Washington Square Collegiate Division; New York University. School of Education
- Series I: Student Notebooks, Between 1891-1906
  Scope and Contents
  Notes from North's courses at New York University School of Pedagogy (1894-1899 and 1905-1906), Washington Square Collegiate Division (1902-1904), National Summer School at Glen Falls, New York (1891-1892), Clark University Summer School (1899).
  - National Summer School at Glen Falls, New York, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Summer School at Glen Falls, New York, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1894-1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1898-1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1899 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clark University Summer School, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Washington Square Collegiate Division (NYU), 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Washington Square Collegiate Division (NYU), 1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Washington Square Collegiate Division (NYU), 1904 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1905 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1905 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - School of Pedagogy (NYU), 1905-1906 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Series II: Student Compositions, 1903-1904
  Written by North for New York University courses, 1903-1904.
  - Compositions, 1903-1904 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Debate Notes, 1890
  North's notes presumably for three debates in which he participated, 1890.
  - Debate Notes, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series IV: Lectures, Between 1903-1906
  Several handwritten lectures (and drafts) of North's travel lectures; advertisements for North's services as lecturer.
  - Manchuria, Iceland, New Zealand, 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Russia, Siberia, Russo-Japanese, circa 1903 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series V: Notebooks, 1904-1905
  Two notebooks containing mixed notes by North, 1904 and 1905.
  - Advertisements for North's lectures, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mixed Notes, 1904-1905 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series VI: Ocean County Schools, 1893-1902
  Materials from North's activities as principal of Toms River High School (1893-1896) and as superintendent of the Ocean County Schools (1897-1902); included are hand-copied student newspapers, 1894-1896; reports of the superintendent, 1897-1902; and letter books used as texts written by North while traveling abroad, 1900-1901.
  - Letter books from North to students, 1900-1901 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Address: Supt. North's address before the Ocean County School Board Association, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Report: Ocean County School Board Association annual report including address by Supt. North, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ledger: The Daily Star of Toms River High School., 1893-1894 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ledger: The Daily Star of Toms River High School, 1895-1896 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Volume: Bound annual reports of Supt. North of Ocean County Schools, N.J.., 1897-1902 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlet: "Suggestions for Schools of Ocean County, N.J.", by F.A. North, County Supt., 1902 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Record book: Ocean County Pedagogical Library records. Titles and authors of collection, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 6)